<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Jerónimo Luza</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Jerónimo Luza</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 16:25:52 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Processing MODIS NDVI Data in Python: Transforming Multidimensional Arrays to Polygons</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/processing-ndvi-data-in-python-transforming-multidimensional-arrays-to-polygons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 16:25:52 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/processing-ndvi-data-in-python-transforming-multidimensional-arrays-to-polygons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I had the opportunity to work with NASA&amp;rsquo;s MODIS NDVI data. I developed a program that takes an area of interest, a start date, and an end date, then downloads the corresponding data from NASA archives. The program leverages parallel processing to efficiently convert NDVI raster data into vectorized polygons. In this blog post, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my approach and insights from the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;./images/MOD13Q1.A2009257.h13v09.061.2021142080827.png&#34; alt=&#34;250m 16 days NDVI readings over northern Brazil&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extract Road Network Data for Administrative Regions With R</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/extract-osm-road-network-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 16:25:52 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/extract-osm-road-network-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;./images/ARG_highways.png&#34; alt=&#34;Road Network in Buenos Aires City&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most common data requests in geospatial data science is obtaining the road network within a given administrative boundary. This includes identifying road locations, classifying road types, and calculating the total road length within a region—an essential analysis for various applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenStreetMap (OSM) is widely recognized as the go-to source for road network data, thanks to its crowdsourced contributions that provide global coverage. To step outside my usual Python development, I decided to create an R function to extract OSM road network data for a given administrative boundary. This function generates a CSV containing the roads&amp;rsquo; linestrings within the boundary and, if requested, also exports a PNG visualizing the results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Perito Moreno Glacier Loss with Sentinel-2</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/mapping-perito-moreno-glacier-loss-with-sentinel-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 16:25:52 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/mapping-perito-moreno-glacier-loss-with-sentinel-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The next article is an ArcGIS StoryMap embedded in an iframe. Some features may not work correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/f223a7c46cc54c049f373b41f437722d?cover=false&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;9000px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen allow=&#34;geolocation&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bypassing AWS Athena &#34;Query Exhausted Resources&#34; using H3 Hexagons</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/bypassing-athena-query-exhausted-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 16:25:52 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/bypassing-athena-query-exhausted-resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you work with Amazon Web Services (AWS) Athena SQL, chances are that you&amp;rsquo;ve encountered the following error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Query exhausted resources at this scale factor&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This generally indicates that you are hitting memory limits on the Athena cluster that runs your query (&lt;a href=&#34;https://repost.aws/questions/QU5M0ASE-_R_mvSMXDWrnuDA/athena-version-3-error-query-exhausted-resources-at-this-scale-factor&#34;&gt;reference 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://repost.aws/questions/QUdYYEXbb0QMuKX6TwDl17GA/athena-query-exhausted-resources-at-this-scale-factor&#34;&gt;reference 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://repost.aws/knowledge-center/athena-query-exhausted&#34;&gt;reference 3&lt;/a&gt;). AWS provides several &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/athena/latest/ug/performance-tuning.html&#34;&gt;performance optimization strategies&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/athena/latest/ug/performance-tuning-data-optimization-techniques.html&#34;&gt;data optimization&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/athena/latest/ug/performance-tuning-query-optimization-techniques.html&#34;&gt;query optimization&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/athena/latest/ug/partition-projection.html#partition-projection-using&#34;&gt;data partitioning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to bypass Athena’s resource limitations for large geospatial queries is to segment intersection operations into a structured sequence of steps. For example, instead of attempting to intersect a large number of small polygons with line geometries all at once—which can cause queries to fail—one can first intersect the lines with larger enclosing geometries, such as administrative boundaries or grid cells. This initial step acts as a filter, identifying only the linestrings that intersect with these larger geometries. The next step is to take these filtered lines and intersect them with the smaller polygons contained within the intersected larger geometries. By introducing more intermediate steps, we further reduce the number of geometries processed at each stage, making it easier for Athena to handle the query efficiently and preventing resource exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extract PM2.5 Pixels and Convert Them to H3 Hexagons</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/extract-pm25-pixels-and-convert-them-to-h3-hexagons/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 20:45:52 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/extract-pm25-pixels-and-convert-them-to-h3-hexagons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I had the opportunity to work with the PM2.5 data provided by the Washington University in St. Louis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initiative comprises a collection of estimated global and regional annual and monthly satellite-derived ground-level fine particulate matter (PM2.5) gridded datasets (&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acsestair.3c00054&#34;&gt;Shen et al., 2024&lt;/a&gt;), spanning the years 1998 to 2022. This collection combines Aerosol Optical Depth (AOD) retrievals from NASA MODIS, MISR, and SeaWIFS, and is available at resolutions 0.01º x 0.01º and 0.1º x 0.1º. For more details and downloading information, visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.wustl.edu/acag/datasets/surface-pm2-5/&#34;&gt;Satellite-derived PM2.5&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
